またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
Nobody knows that I can see Youkai.
妖怪が見えるのはみんなには秘密だ
あ 傘が飛ばされてる
There's an umbrella flying.
傘
An umbrella?
Where? Where?
どこ どこ
Look, over there.
ほら あそこだって
Where'd you say it was? Where is it?
どこだって どこ
Where is it?
いや 見間違いだろう
Oh, it must've been a mistake.
Really?
そっか
じゃあな 夏目
Later, Natsume.
明日な
See you tomorrow!
Yeah!
You can see me, human child?
私が見えるのか 人の子よ
Asagi's Koto
Then let me tell you this.
では お主に致そう
I don't want to touch any humans, but I don't have a choice.
人間など触れたくないが 仕方あるまい
Your body is mine.
お前の体を頂くぞ
S-Stop.
よ よせ
Now, give it to me.
さあ 寄越せ
Stop!
やめんか
I told you to stop!
止めろってんだろ
You're really short-tempered.
お前 本当に気が短いな
Nyanko-sensei...
にゃんこ先生
ほれ カルシウムだ 食え
There's some calcium, so eat it up.
No thanks.
要らない
Damn it, how careless of me.
くそ 俺としたことが
人間のくせに なかなかやるじゃねえか
You're pretty good for a human.
よし 何が何でもその体を頂こう
All right! I'll have that body by any means!
What do you want?
何なんだよ
Wait, Akagane.
お待ちなさい アカガネ
人の子よ この者の無礼をお許しください
Human child, please forgive his rudeness.
He did it all for me.
すべて私のために
There's a voice coming from the gourd.
瓢箪から声が
Don't talk, Asagi. You'll get tired.
アサギ 喋るな 疲れてしまうぞ
I...
私は
眠ってしまったようだ
She fell asleep.
アサギ 聞いた名だ
Asagi... I've heard that name before.
There's an illusionary city where nobles gather.
高貴な者達が集う幻の里 磯月の森に
Some say that there's a beautiful koto player named Asagi in Isozuki Forest.
アサギという美しい蒼琴弾きがいると聞くが
So she's that Asagi?
あのアサギか
That's right.
そうだ
However, she fell ill and became unable to play the koto.
だが 体を病んで琴を弾くこともできなくなり 里へ返されたんだ
She was forced to go back home.
よく笑う奴だったのに
She used to laugh often, too.
すっかり元気がなくなった
Then suddenly, she became unwell.
So, human child, for Asagi's sake, lend that body...
だから人の子よ アサギのために しばらくその体を
If you don't listen to me, I'll bite off your ears and nose!
言うことを聞かねば その耳か鼻かを食い千切ってやるぞ
貸せ 寄越せ
Hand it over!
Hold it, you shrimp!
待て こら低級 これは私のだ
He's mine!
ああ 狸に噛まれた
A raccoon dog bit me!
What'd you say?!
何だと
Don't laugh, Jizou!
笑うな 地蔵
Nothing good comes from carelessly getting involved with Ayakashi.
妖にうかつに関わると ろくなことにはならない
ましてや体を貸すなんて
And even worse, lending them your body?
よく笑う奴だったのに
She used to often laugh, too.
でも少し 気の毒な気がした
However...
I kind of pitied them.
I'm back...
ただいま
Morning, Nyanko-sensei.
あ おはよう にゃんこ先生
Coming back in the morning again?
また朝帰りか
夏目 その髪
Natsume, your hair...
My eyes are kind of blue as well.
瞳の色も なんか蒼い
Why did this happen?
なんでこんなことに
あれ 戻った
Huh? It's back to normal.
Was it just my imagination?
気のせいだったのか
Hey!
おーい おはよう 夏目
Morning, Natsume.
Ah, good morning.
あ はい おはようございます
M-Morning, Kitamoto.
お おはよう 北本
Th-That surprised me. I thought I had the wrong person for a moment.
び びっくりした 一瞬人違いかと思った
あっは ごめん
Sorry.
Ew, what's with those two?
なんなのこの二人
Natsume.
夏目 辞書ありがとう
Thanks for the dictionary.
It was a big help.
助かったよ
Yeah...
夏目 落としたぞ
You dropped it, Natsume.
ありがとう 田沼
Thanks, Tanuma!
田沼
Tanuma?
あ いや 一瞬 夏目が女の人に見えたんだけど
Well, I thought you were a girl for a moment.
Sorry, I just imagined it.
すまん 気のせいだ
S-Sorry!
す すみません
で この三代将軍 徳川家光が
Leaving Kitamoto aside,
北本はともかく
if Tanuma could feel something, then could it be...
田沼が何かを感じるってことは まさか
You did something, didn't you?
お前 何かしたな
I placed Asagi inside your body while you were sleeping.
眠ってる間に アサギをお前の体の中に入れさせてもらった
Looks like she's adapting to you well.
うまいこと同化できてるみたいだな
Well, I pray that you'll cooperate for a while.
まあ しばらく協力願おう
はあ 今朝の青い髪も目も 憑依の現れだったのか
So the blue hair and eyes from this morning were the manifestation of being possessed.
Forgive me.
申し訳ありません
I told him to stop,
止めるように言ったのですが
but I had no way to control myself. Sorry.
制止する術もなく 申し訳ございません
この声 お前がアサギか
This voice... You're Asagi?
Please don't blame him.
どうかあの者を咎めないでください
It's my fault.
悪いのは私なのです
It's okay, you don't need to apologize.
いいよ 謝らなくても
I'm sorry.
申し訳ありません
体から出してやる方法
A way to get her out of your body?
Yeah, something not too violent.
ああ 頭突き以外でな
Well, then you have no choice but to grant Asagi's wish.
ふん じゃ アサギの希望を叶えるしかないな
When she feels satisfied, I'm sure she'll leave your body naturally.
気持ちが消化されれば 自然と体から剥がれていくだろう
うーん でも 希望ったって
But her wish?
There's no point in complaining.
グタグタ言っててもしょうがないだろう
さっさと済ませて帰るぞ 人の子よ
Hurry up and finish this so we can go back, human child.
You shouldn't be the one talking.
お前が言うな
どこから湧いた 名前は何だ
Where'd you come from? What's your name?
I don't give my name to mere humans.
人間ごときに名乗る名はない
Then your name is Bullseye from now on.
じゃあお前は今から 蛇の目さんだ
After the bullseye from a bullseye-patterned umbrella.
蛇の目傘の蛇の目
B-Bullseye?!
じゃ 蛇の目さん
お迎い ご苦労さん
Thanks for coming to pick us up!
Damned raccoon dog!
なんと
Ah, what a cute name.
まあ 可愛い名前
Aren't you glad, Bullseye?
よかったですね 蛇の目さん
Even you too, Asagi?
アサギ お前まで
いいでしょう 楽しいじゃないですか
Come on, isn't it fun?
アサギ
Asagi...
This is creepy!
気持ち 悪い
今 体を乗っ取られた
My body was just taken over.
あ ついうっかり 申し訳ありません
Ah, I was too careless.
Forgive me.
All right, enough. I'll help you.
分かった分かった
協力するから 琴が弾けたら 離れるんだろう
You'll leave once you can play the koto, right?
Of course!
もちろんだ
So, we have to start by making the koto?
で 琴を作るところから
Right, since it's a special koto after all.
ああ 特別な琴だからな
額に白い線のある線引きって言う鯉そっくりの妖がいるから
There's an Ayakashi called senbiki that looks like a carp with a white string in its body.
That's what we're going to catch.
そいつを捕まえる
だから何で魚を
So why do we need to catch a fish?
何 つべこべ言うな
What? Stop complaining!
What's with that gloomy face?
なんだ そのしけた面は
俺はやるぜぇ
I'm going to catch it!
あー 疲れた
I'm tired...
出て来い
Come on out!
Forgive us, Natsume-sama.
申し訳ありません 夏目様
No, it's okay.
あ いや
What kind of relationship do you and Bullseye have?
アサギと蛇の目さんは どういう関係なんだい
付き合ってるとか
Are you going out?
まさか 蛇の目さんは傘持ちだったのです
Not at all.
He was an umbrella holder.
Umbrella holder?
傘持ち
In Isozuki Forest, those with talent would come to calm the forest where the god Mibu-sama lived.
磯月の森には
森を治める壬生様が見初めた才のあるもの達が集まっておりました
There would be those who held umbrellas for Mibu-sama and the others there.
そこで 壬生様やそれらのもの達に傘をさしかけたり
Bullseye's duty was to protect everyone as a bodyguard.
用心棒として皆を守るのが 蛇の目さんのお役目なのです
He is very skilled.
蛇の目さんはとても腕が立つのですよ
Isozuki was a beautiful place, much like a dream.
磯月は美しいところでした 夢のように
I wanted to always be there.
いつまでもいたかった
ずっと壬生様のお傍で生きていくのだと思っていた
I thought I would always live by Mibu-sama's side.
ずっとずっと
Forever...
and ever...
引けなくなったからって追い出すなんて
But he banished you because you couldn't play anymore?
What a small-minded god.
ずいぶん 了見の狭い神様じゃないか
いいえ 夏目様
No, Natsume-sama.
Mibu-sama picked me up because I didn't have my own place.
居場所も持たなかった私を 壬生様は拾ってくださったのです
役に立てなくなったことに耐えられず飛び出したのは私の方
I ran away because I couldn't stand being useless.
いたぞ 線引きだ
I got one! It's a senbiki!
I caught it!
捕ったぞ
See? This is used for the string.
ほら見ろ この糸を弦に使うんだ
So is this all we need for materials?
じゃあ 材料集めはこれで終わり
いや 次は胴だ
No.
Next is the body.
What?
切り株を探すぞ
We're going to search for a tree stump.
それも頭が出たばかりの竹の子に がんがん貫かれてるものだ
And it's got to be one with bamboo shoots that have just started growing out of it!
A little longer... A little longer and you can play.
もう少し もう少しで弾かせてやる
蛇の目さんは本当に アサギのことが
Bullseye, really...
まあ どうしたの そんなに濡れちゃって
How'd you get so wet?
ああ いえ
Ah, well...
Ah, I need to get you a towel.
あ タオルタオル
Ah, Takashi-kun might catch a cold...
やだ 貴志君が風邪引いちゃう
I'm really okay!
本当 大丈夫ですから
See?
ほらほら はい よく拭いて
All right, dry yourself thoroughly.
Your nose is all wet too.
肌も本当にびっしょりよ
I was always there.
いつまでもいたかった ずっと
Forever...
All right. Go take a bath, okay?
さあ お風呂に入ってらっしゃい ねえ
It just heated up, too.
ちょうど沸いたばかりだから 早く入りなさいね
Hurry up and get in, okay?
How long will I be able to stay here?
俺はいつまでここにいられるんだろう
Was that a dream?
今のは 夢
いや アサギの
No, Asagi's?
蛇の目さん
Bullseye...
You've awoken, Natsume.
起こしたか 夏目
Yeah, but Asagi's asleep.
でも アサギは眠ってるぞ
話したいなら
If you want to talk...
Asagi's fingers can no longer play the koto.
アサギの指ではもう琴は弾けない
She has a sickness where her body dries up like dirt and crumbles.
体が乾いた土のように崩れていく病気だ
もう戻れない
She can't go back to being normal.
だが ほかの器に移ってる間は進行が遅くなる
However, while she is in another body, its progression will slow down.
I'm grateful to you, Natsume.
感謝している 夏目
あいつが笑っているのを見たのは 壬生様の御前で
The last time I saw her laugh was when she happily played her instrument for Mibu-sama.
幸せそうに楽を奏でていたのが最後だった
その演奏中
And during her performance...
her body suddenly began to crumble.
突然肌が崩れ始めた
Her white slender fingers and her bright cheeks were lost before her admired Mibu-sama.
白くのびる指も 光る頬も
憧れてやまない壬生様の前で
明日は満月 磯月への道が一時だけ開く
Tomorrow is a full moon.
The path to Isozuki will open for a short time.
I want her to play before Mibu-sama, even if only once.
最後にもう一度だけでも 壬生様の前で弾かせてやりたい
それまでどうか お力を 夏目殿
Please help us until then, Natsume-dono.
Why are you doing this, Bullseye?
蛇の目さんはどうして
どうしてそんなにも
Why do you go so far?
I...
俺は
Hello, Akagane.
こんにちは アカガネ
I...
俺は ただの傘持ちさ
I'm just an umbrella holder.
Damn, I just can't find one!
くそ なかなかないもんだなあ
ぜ 全然見つからないぞ
Where are you?!
どこだ 切り株
We can't find any.
Is it even here?
本当にあるのか ここに
Are you looking for something?
何かお探しか
A tree stump with a bamboo shoot growing out of it.
竹の生えた切り株を
There's one in that thicket over there.
それならほれ その藪の中を
You're right, there it is!
あ 本当だ あった
え 今俺 何と会話を
What was I talking with just now?
I told you. I told you!
教えてやったぞ 教えてやったぞ
In exchange, I will have your guts!
代わりに お前の腸をもらおう
Damn, I talked with some weird Youkai.
しまった 変な妖怪と口をきいてしまったか
Hey, Natsume! Are you even looking?
おい 夏目
ちゃんと探してるか
You did it, Natsume! This is it!
でかしたぞ 夏目 これだ
All right, time to start carving it!
よーし 早速削りだすぞ
I'm feeling sick.
気分が悪くなってきた
このざらっとした熱っぽいだるさは アサギのか
Is this feverish pain Asagi's?
If she performs when she's this weak...
こんなに弱って演奏なんかしたら アサギの命が
Her life will...
Are you okay?
大丈夫ですか 申し訳ありません
I'm sorry you have to go through this because of me.
わたしのせいで
Oh yeah, I haven't confirmed this with you yet.
そういえば 確認してなかったけど
Yes?
はい
アサギも琴を弾きたいのか
Do you want to play the koto too?
If I were given...
もしもう一度
もう一度その機会があるのであれば 私は
If I were given that chance once more, I...
I'm not dexterous and I have stiff fingers, so you might not be able to play well.
俺は器用じゃないし指も硬くて うまく弾けないかもしれないよ
Is that still okay with you?
それでもいいのかい
Yes.
Asagi, did you know?
アサギ 知ってるかい
Akagane always, always...
アカガネはずっと ずっと 君のことが
I did it! Wake up, Natsume!
できた 夏目 起きろ
Thank goodness.
よかった
We can still make it. Let's go.
まだ間に合う 行くぞ
Akagane? What is it? What's going-
アカガネ どうしたんです
一体何の
Asagi, the path to Isozuki is still open right now.
アサギ 今ならまだ磯月の森への道が開いてる
Go and...
行っておいで
そして 壬生様に
I found you!
見つけたぞ
We promised! I'm here for your guts!
約束だ 腸をもらいに来た
The one from before!
あの時の
あ アカガネ
Akagane...
Damn it!
しまった
The koto is...
あ 琴が
Asagi's... Bullseye's... precious...
アサギの 蛇の目さんの 大切な
Natsume!
夏目
Natsume.
夏目 夏目
Natsume!
Are you okay?
大丈夫か
Y-Yeah...
あいつは追い払った
I chased him away.
琴は
How about the koto?
It's safe. You protected it.
無事だ お前が守ってくれた
I see, that's great.
そうか よかった
Think you can stand?
立てそうか 急げばまだなんとか間に合う
We can make it if we hurry.
If you can't, I'll carry you.
無理なら 俺が抱えていく
蛇の目さんこそ そんな怪我で
What about you, Bullseye? You can't go with those wounds.
行こう 夏目
Let's go, Natsume.
Let's go!
行こう
I thought that if it were possible, I would like to play once more.
叶うなら もう一度だけでも弾きたいと思った
I always, always played only for him.
ずっと ずっとあの方のためにだけ弾いて来た
So...
だから もし もう一度弾くことが叶うのなら
If I could play once more,
it would be for my kind and precious friend.
優しくて大切な友人のため
あなたのために弾きたいと思っていた
I wanted to play for you.
Will you listen, Akagane?
アカガネ 聞いてくれますか
I could hear music from far away.
遠くで音楽が聞こえた
A beautiful sound that I had never heard before.
But even so, that sound...
それでも その音は
came from my fingers and made the air vibrate.
僕の指から
空気を揺らして
Asagi left my body as if she was falling towards the sky.
まるで空へ落ちるように アサギは僕から剥がれていった
Thanks for everything.
世話になったな
これからどうするんだ
What are you going to do now?
I'll take Asagi and return to my home.
アサギを連れて 里へ帰る
I see.
そうか
She's just in a deep, deep sleep.
深く深く眠っただけだよ
Yeah.
うん またな アサギ
See you, Asagi.
またな 蛇の目さん
See you, Bullseye.
Yeah.
See you, Natsume!
またな 夏目
どこ行ってたんだよ 先生 人が大変な時に
Where'd you go when I was in trouble, sensei?
Feel better now, nice guy?
気が済んだか お人好しめ
I'm hungry. Buy me some steamed buns.
腹が減ったぞ 饅頭買ってくれ
Nanatsuji isn't open yet.
まだ七辻屋は開いてないぞ
Wh-What?!
な なんだと
Was there a place where you wanted to be forever, Nyanko-sensei?
にゃんこ先生はずっといたいと思える場所って あったか
ふん そんなもの私には一生必要ないさ
I don't ever need that.
Me too, sensei.
俺もね 先生
ずっと そう思っていたんだけどなあ
That's what I always thought, anyway.
I-Idiot! Don't hug me!
な バカ 抱きしめるな
Let go! Let go!
放せ 放せんか
I tried to play on what they left behind,
残されていた琴を弾いてみたけれど
but that beautiful sound never came from it again.
もう あんな美しい音は出なかった
That sound didn't come from my fingers, but played through her heart.
あの音は 俺の指ではなく 彼女の心が奏でたのだろう
Breakfast is ready!
朝ご飯よ
Okay!
はーい
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
夕立の雨上がりに
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
Nyanko's Book of Boredom
Ah, sensei! What are you doing?
あ 先生 なんてことを
I wouldn't do that.
私がそんなことをするものか
Don't play dumb! Get out!
とぼけるな 出て行け
Sure, I'll get out! You idiot!
ああ出て行ってやるわい 夏目のバーカ
そして私は穴に落ちた
And then I fell into a hole.
わあ 白い小豚が降ってきた
Ah! A white piglet fell!